<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Contentment in Gods gifts or some sermon notes leading to equanimitie and contentation. By Henry Mason parson of S. Andrews Vndershaft London</title>
            <author>Mason, Henry, 1573?-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07203</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102845</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838607</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838607</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2992</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07203)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2992)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1145:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Contentment in Gods gifts or some sermon notes leading to equanimitie and contentation. By Henry Mason parson of S. Andrews Vndershaft London</title>
                  <author>Mason, Henry, 1573?-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 123, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by M. Flesher] for Iohn Clarke, and are to be sold at his shop under S. Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2992:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2992:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Contentment IN GODS GIFTS OR Some Sermon Notes leading to equanimitie and contentation.</p>
            <p>BY HENRY MASON Parſon of S. Andrews Vnderſhaft London.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for IOHN CLARKE, and are to be ſold at his ſhop under S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2992:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2992:2"/>
            <head>CONTENTMENT IN GODS GIFTS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOHN 20.3, 4, 5, 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Peter therefore went forth, and that other Diſciple, and came to the Sepulchre.</p>
                  <p>So they ran both together, and the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſciple did out-runne Peter, and came firſt to the Sepulchre.</p>
                  <p>And hee ſtooping downe and looking in, ſaw the lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen clothes lying, yet went he not in.</p>
                  <p>Then commeth Simon Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following him, and went into the Sepulchre.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His chapter doth eſpecially co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine the Manifeſtation
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2992:3"/>of <hi>Chriſts Reſurrection:</hi> and that is here ſet out by 3 ſorts of proofes. 1 By ſenſible <hi>Tokens;</hi> 2 by the <hi>Teſtimonie</hi> of Angels, and 3 by the <hi>Apparitions</hi> of our Lord himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The ſenſible <hi>Tokens,</hi> which are one proofe of Chriſts Reſurrection, are theſe (1) The ſtone rolled away, (2) the grave open (3) the bodie remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and (4) the linnen clothes left behind in the grave: and theſe are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the ten firſt verſes. Where we may more particularly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how they were repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, firſt to <hi>Marie Magdalen,</hi> in the two firſt verſes; and then to <hi>Peter</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2992:3"/>and <hi>Iohn,</hi> in the eight verſes following: which is that parcell of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which I have now taken for my Text.</p>
            <p>And herein we may note foure things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe two Apoſtles. (1) Their <hi>diligence</hi> in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after Chriſt. v. 3, 4, &amp; part of the 5. (2) Their <hi>happines</hi> in finding cleare Tokens of his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Hee ſeeth the linnen clothes lie, &amp;c.</hi> v. 6, 7, and part of the 8. (3) Their <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe</hi> as touching Chriſts Reſurrection, <hi>And hee ſaw and believed: for as yet they knew not &amp;c.</hi> v. 8, 9. and (4.) The Conſequent or concluſion of this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, <hi>Then the Diſciples
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2992:4"/>went away againe to their owne home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ye have the ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis and coherence of this Text. I now goe back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to conſider more diſtinctly of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and firſt of the <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> of theſe Diſciples in ſeeking after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in theſe wordes; <hi>Peter therefore went forth, and that other Diſciple,</hi> &amp;c. In which words I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider againe two things. 1 Their ioynt &amp; agreeing endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; <hi>Peter went forth and that other Diſciple, and came to the ſepulchre: ſo they ran both together.</hi> 2 Their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall &amp; diſagreeing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances; <hi>The other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple did outrunne Peter and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2992:4"/>came firſt,</hi> &amp;c. The ſumme and ſcope whereof is this, that <hi>Iohn</hi> ranne faſter, and came ſooner; and <hi>Peter</hi> went further in, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered better of the things that had happened.</p>
            <p>In all which paſſage the words are ſo plaine and eaſie, that I may ſay of them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore. Scr.</hi> 205. <hi>pag.</hi> 324. <hi>C.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> did of another Text of the Goſpell [<hi>Auditarem ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis atque factorem, quàm Expoſitore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſiderant</hi>] they need no <hi>expoſition</hi> to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold them; they require rather <hi>uttent on</hi> to marke them, and <hi>obedience</hi> to doe that which we are taught by them. And therefore without inſiſting on the words, I come to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2992:5"/>of ſome Notes.</p>
            <p n="1">1 And firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>1</label> I note that the Diſciples of Chriſt had <hi>difference of gifts;</hi> and though they were but two, and both of them A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, yet they were not qualified alike. The Text ſaith, that <hi>Iohn</hi> did <hi>out-runne Peter,</hi> and came ſooner to the ſepulchre; but that <hi>Peter</hi> went fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in and obſerved all things better: and from hence learned men doe gather, that <hi>Iohn</hi> was more quick, but <hi>Peter</hi> more ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: &amp; out of other Texts of the Goſpell I may adde further, that <hi>Iohn</hi> was the <hi>beloued Diſciple,</hi> and one of Chriſts kinred; but <hi>Peter</hi> was the <hi>head ſcholar,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2992:5"/>and is named firſt among the Apoſtles. And from hence I obſerve,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>
               </label> that</p>
            <p>Good men are not alike endued with all good parts. And herein I ſay two things, 1 That good men are not alike qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among themſelves, as in this place <hi>Peter</hi> was not ſo quick as <hi>Iohn,</hi> nor <hi>Iohn</hi> ſo ſolid as <hi>Peter</hi> was. 2 That one man is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like qualified with all gifts; as here <hi>Iohn</hi> was very ſpeedy in running to the Sepulchre, but not ſo wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in obſeruing what had happened. Of both theſe ſeverally, and by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Good men are not alike qualified,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>1</label> one as an
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2992:6"/>other is. For confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof my proofes ſhall bee of two ſorts, 1 From particular exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: and 2 from generall teſtimonies.</p>
            <p n="1">I. And firſt for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar examples,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>2</label> we find that there were manie good kings in the land of <hi>Iudah,</hi> but <hi>none like Ioſiah and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah.</hi> 2 King. 18.5. and 2 King. 23.25. and manie <hi>meeke</hi> men no doubt there were among the Prophets and people of God, but <hi>none like unto Moſes.</hi> Num. 12.3. and many perfect and upright men in the world, but <hi>none like unto Iob nall the earth.</hi> Iob 1.8. and many ſincere and <hi>well minded</hi> in the Chriſtian
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2992:6"/>Church, but <hi>none like mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Timothie.</hi> Phil. 2.20. And ſo when the Lord ſpeaking of his fierce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt the land, ſaith that <hi>if Noah, Daniel &amp; Iob were in it, they ſhould deliver but their own ſoules by their righteouſneſſe:</hi> Ezek. 14.14. he implyeth that theſe were three principal men, ſuch as the world had fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like them in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and holineſſe of life. And when S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of <hi>Iames, Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> that they were eſteemed <hi>pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars</hi> in the Church: <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.9. he implyeth, that they were principall Teachers, and prime Apoſtles, and men of ſpeciall worth and account. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. <hi>Luke</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2992:7"/>ſaith, that the Apoſtles and Elders did <hi>ſend cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen men of their company, namely Barſabas and Silas,</hi> who were <hi>chiefe among the brethren:</hi> Act. 15.22. hee meaneth that they were knowne to be men of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall fidelity &amp; truſt. And by theſe &amp; ſuch like exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples it appeareth that all good men are not qali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied alike.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>2</label> for teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Scripture; I wil on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, where he ſaith, <hi>To eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of us is given grace according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt:</hi> Eph. 4.7. and that of our Sauiour
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 25 15.</note> in the Parable, where it is ſaid, that the Maſter
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2992:7"/>of the houſe, (in whoſe perſon God Almighty is deciphered) <hi>gave to one ſervant five Talents, to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two, &amp; to another one; to everyman according to his ſeverall ability.</hi> In theſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages I note three things. 1 The ſeverall perſons, to whom God conferreth his gifts, to one, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and a third, <hi>to every one of them;</hi> ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: or (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) <hi>to every one of us,</hi> who bee Gods ſervants. 2 The different gifts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on theſe perſons, <hi>To one he giuethone Talent, to another two, and to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther five,</hi> and to everyone a <hi>meaſure</hi> of grace and of good things. 3 The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2992:8"/>that God obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in beſtowing theſe gifts of his: it is, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>according to the meaſure of the gift of God.</hi> .i. According to that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which God is pleaſed to give: (or as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſpeaketh) it is <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to everie mans ſeverall abilitie</hi> .i. He giueth ſuch and ſo much as hee ſeeth everyman is fit to make uſe of for Gods glory, and the common good. Both proportions are iuſt and right, and both of them ſhould bee ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this ſort: God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth his gifts vpon men in a different kinde and meaſure, even accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as himſelfe pleaſeth;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2992:8"/>and ſo hee pleaſeth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them, as hee ſeeth men are able to uſe them for the good of his Church and the glory of his name.</p>
            <p>Theſe briefely bee the proofes: by which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith of <hi>Starres</hi> in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, though all be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in their kind, yet that <hi>one ſtarre differeth from an other ſtarre in glorie:</hi> 1 Cor. 15.41. ſo we may ſay of the Saints upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, that though all of them be <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>righteous,</hi> yet one dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth from another in graces and goodneſſe. And ſo much for proofe and declaration of the firſt point.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2992:9"/>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond is,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>2</label> that the ſame man is not alike gifted with all good things. For confirmation hereof,</p>
            <p n="1">I.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>1</label> My firſt proofe ſhall bee from the Text of the Apoſtle, 1 Cor. 12.4. &amp;c. <hi>There are diverſities of gifts, but the ſame Spirit: and there are differences of adminiſtrations,</hi> &amp;c. and verſ, 8. 9. &amp;c. <hi>To one is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the word of wiſedome, to another the word of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> &amp;c. and verſe 17. <hi>If the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where were the ſmelling?</hi> and verſe 29. <hi>Are all Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? are all Prophets? &amp;c.</hi> In theſe words the Apoſtle
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2992:9"/>doth at large ſet downe the point in hand: but more particularly we may note that hee declareth it three wayes, 1 Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, when he ſaith, <hi>There are diverſities,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatively, when hee ſaith, <hi>Are all Apoſtles,</hi> &amp;c? 3 By way of compariſon or ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, when hee ſaith,
<note n="*" place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>For as the body is one, and hath many members,</hi> &amp;c. and, <hi>If the whole body were an eye, where were the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> &amp;c. which is, as if hee ſhould ſay, It is in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Body of Chriſt, as it is in the naturall bodie of a man. In the naturall bodie there are many members, and euery mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber hath its ſeuerall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2992:10"/>differing and diſtinct from other, for <hi>the eye</hi> hath the faculty of <hi>ſeeing,</hi> but not of hearing or ſmelling; and the <hi>eare</hi> hath the faculty of <hi>hearing,</hi> but not of ſeeing, or ſpeaking; and the <hi>noſe</hi> hath the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>ſmelling,</hi> but not of ſeeing, or hearing, or taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c. And ſo in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy myſticall; the offices of men are different, one is a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> another is a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate,</hi> another is a <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,</hi> &amp; another a <hi>Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Their intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall gifts are different, one hath a good wit, but not ſo good a iudgment; another hath a ſound iudgement, but not ſo ready a wit; and a third
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2992:10"/>hath wit and iudgement, but wanteth memory and utterance. And laſtly their graces of ſanctification are different: one is more zealous, another is more ſetled, a third is more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainted, a fourth is more freehearted, &amp;c. and every where we may ſee that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified which the Apoſtle hath ſaid, <hi>Every man hath his proper gift of God; one after this maner, and another after that.</hi> 1 Cor. 7.7.</p>
            <p n="2">II. A ſecond proofe may bee from experience, and examples of all ages. In Scriptures wee finde that <hi>Rachel</hi> was <hi>faire,</hi> but not <hi>fruitfull,</hi> and that <hi>Leah</hi> was <hi>fruitful,</hi> but not <hi>faire,</hi> Geneſ. 29.17, 31. And ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2992:11"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was <hi>prudent,</hi> but not <hi>eloquent.</hi> Exod. 4.10.16. And <hi>Solomon</hi> was <hi>wiſe,</hi> but not <hi>chaſt.</hi> 1 King. 3.12. &amp; 11.1. Againe <hi>Nabal</hi> was a <hi>rich man,</hi> but hee was a <hi>foole.</hi> 1 Sam. 25.2, 25. <hi>Iephtah</hi> was <hi>a man of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,</hi> but <hi>hee was a baſtard.</hi> Iudg. 11.1. and <hi>Naaman was a great and an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man, but hee was a Leper.</hi> 2 King. 5.1. And in our dayes, wee ſee ſome are rich but fooliſh; and ſome are wiſe, but unfortunate, and ſome are wittie, but unſetled: and ſome have one gift, &amp; ſome another, but no one man hath all.</p>
            <p>Theſe be the proofes: the point will yet be more plaine, and more fit for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2992:11"/>uſe and application, if we conſider the reaſons, why God hath thus diſpoſed of his gifts. And they bee theſe and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 1. One reaſon, why God doth thus different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtribute his gifts, may be, becauſe he would ſhew himſelfe as a free <hi>Doner,</hi> ſo a wiſe <hi>Diſpoſer</hi> of all things. For if one man ſhould have all abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; others few or none of any worth; or if all men ſhould have the higheſt and beſt places, and the other gifts ſhould lie undiſpoſed of: the world might ſeeme to bee gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded either by blinde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, or fatall neceſſitie; but providence and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2992:12"/>in fitting all things, one for an others uſe, there could none be ſeen. For as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If the whole bodie were an eye, where were the hearing? and if the whole were hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where were the ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling?</hi> ſo if all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth were Kings, where were the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be gouerned by them? and if the whole Church were Biſhops, where were the Paſtors, or where the flock that ſhould bee fed by them? and if all Citizens were Aldermen, where were the Common<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ers? and if every freeman were a Merchant, where were the ſhop-keeper, and the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2992:12"/>Shoomaker, and the Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and the Water-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and the Seavenger? For there is not the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and moſt deſpicable of all theſe, but hath his neceſſarie uſe, ſo that the greateſt or the wealthieſt Potentate cannot tell how to be without them. But now that men have their love all offices and their ſever all abilities, by which they are fitted each for anothers ſervice, and all for the beautie &amp; benefit of the whole frame, it is a plaine argument, that the hand of Divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence had the diſpoſing of theſe things; and that God it was, who hath thus <hi>Divided to every man
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2992:13"/>ſeverally, as he will,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2. A ſecond rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be, becauſe God would have men to take notice both of their <hi>gifts</hi> and of their <hi>defects;</hi> that by the one they might learne humilitie, and by the other thankfulneſſe. For if any man had all good parts, he would bee too proud of his perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And as <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> when he <hi>was become ſtrong,</hi> and <hi>his greatneſſe reached unto heaven, and his Dominion to the end of the earth:</hi> then hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted himſelfe againſt God, as if all his greatnes had beene of his owne
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2992:13"/>procuring: <hi>Is not this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>great Babylon, that I have built for the houſe of the kingdome, by the might of my power, and for the honour of my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie?</hi> Dan. 4.22.30. and 5.18, 19, ſo, if any of us had all or the moſt abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, we would preſently conceit, that we had no great need of any further helpe; and that we needed not to pray for ſupply of Gods favour, who had ſo much of our owne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. Againe, if any man were deſtitute of all Gods Mercies among his neighbors; he would want matter to bleſſe God for. But now that God hath given unto men a meaſure
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2992:14"/>of good things; and hath tempered their gifts with many other defects: it is eaſie to ſee, that they are both indebted to God for that which they have, and ſtand in neede of his day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favour for ſupplying of that which they want. And conſequently, this different diſpoſing, of Gods gifts, may teach us both to think <hi>humbly</hi> of our ſelves, and <hi>thankfully</hi> of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A third reaſon may be, becauſe God would give men occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all love</hi> &amp; charity each to other. For if one man had all things, hee would neither have neede to receive helpe from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2992:14"/>not care to doe good unto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of whom he had no neede. But now that one man hath one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, and another man another abilitie; and no man hath all, nor any man nothing: men are hereby made fit, both to do good to others, and to receive good from them back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. This the Apoſtle obſerved in the parts of mans body: that <hi>the eye cannot ſay to the hand, I have no need of thee; nor the head to the feet, I have no neede of you:</hi> but that <hi>God hath</hi> ſo <hi>tempered the bodie together, that there ſhould be noſchiſme in the body, but that the members ſhould have the ſame care, one for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2992:15"/>another.</hi> 1. Cor. 12.21, 24, 25. And ſo we ſee it is: for the eye <hi>ſeeth,</hi> not for it ſelfe onely, but for the whole body, and the eare <hi>heareth,</hi> not for it ſelfe, but for all the other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and ſo the ſtomack doth <hi>concoct</hi> meate, and the liver makes <hi>blood,</hi> and the heart engenders <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> and the feet <hi>move</hi> themſelves, and each one doth his proper office, not for his owne uſe but for the uſe of all the other parts: and by this meanes every one enioyeth all the perfections that all the reſt have. And ſo it is in the civill bodie: The King enacteth Laws, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituteth Iudges, muſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2992:15"/>ſouldiours; it is not for his owne ſafetie one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but for the ſafetie of the whole Realme, without whoſe welfare he could not long enioy his Crowne. And ſo the Preacher ſtudieth the Scriptures, not onely to enforme himſelfe, but to inſtruct others; and the Counſellor ſtudieth the Law, not onely that hee may plead for himſelfe, but more eſpecially for his Clients, and the Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker maketh ſhooes, &amp; the Tailorgarments, and each artificer the worke of his calling, that when they have done their worke they may diſperſe their own commodities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2992:16"/>and by the ſale of them ſupplie themſelves with the commodities of other Trades, wherein they have no skill.</p>
            <p>And hereby it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that there is great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and much wiſdome to be ſeene in this varietie and difference of Gods gifts: it remaineth now onely, that we make a right vſe of it. And it may ſerve us for two uſes: 1 We may learne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation with our owne place and gifts: and 2 We ſhould ſet a due valuation of the gifts beſtowed on other men, without grudging or repining.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. We ſhould he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce learne to be <hi>contented</hi> with that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2992:16"/>place in which God hath ſet us, &amp; with thoſe gifts, which God hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon us. For if God have diſpoſed his gifts in different manner for ſuch good and important rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and more eſpecially in ſuch provident ſort, as is moſt for our owne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; then wee have great cauſe to let God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone with his owne both wiſe and gratious dealing. This leſſon is moſt appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to Murmurers and impatient people, ſuch as are diſcontented with their own lot, &amp; grumble at the welfare of others. Such were thoſe <hi>Laborers</hi> in the Goſpel who having received their full paie,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2992:17"/>yet <hi>murmured againſt the Maſter of the houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 20.11</note> becauſe he had given as much to them that <hi>wrought hut one houre,</hi> as he had done to themſelves; who (as they ſay) <hi>had borne the burden and heate of the day.</hi> And ſuch are they in our daies, who grudge to ſee their equalls preferred, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſit ſtill, where they were; or to ſee their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors thrive in wealth, and themſelves to goe ſlowly forward, or to ſee others reſpected abroad, when themſelves are paſſed by and neglected. And not unlike to theſe are they alſo; who grudge againſt God, becauſe their places are meane, and their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2992:17"/>maintenance too ſmall for men of ſuch parts and abilities. Such men for ſtilling of their queru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous natures, ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1 That they have no right to that; which they do ſo greedily deſire: For all things are Gods, and he may diſpoſe them at his pleaſure. <hi>The earth is the Lords, and the fulneſſe thereof.</hi> Pſal. 24.1. <hi>Every beaſt of the foreſt is his;</hi> and <hi>the cattell,</hi> that be <hi>upon a thouſand hills.</hi> Pſal. 50.10. <hi>The ſilver is mine, and the gold is mine, ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</hi> Hagg. 2.8. And, <hi>thine</hi> (ſaith David) <hi>O Lord, is the greatneſſe, and the power, and the glorie, and the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2992:18"/>victorie and the Maieſtie: for all that is in the heavens and in the earth is thine: thine is the kingdome, O Lord, and thou art exalted as head above all.</hi> 1 Chron. 29.11. And if all be Gods, why doth man laie claime to any thing, as his due? Or, if nothing be due to him, why ſhould hee grudge for want of that, whereto he hath no right? Sure it was a reaſonable ſpeech of the good-man of the houſe, when he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the grumbling <hi>Labourer, Is it not lawfull for me to doe what I will with mine owne?</hi> Mat. 20.15. And ſo if any of us ſhall murmure, becauſe others are advanced to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2992:18"/>offices, when we ſit ſtill in our place below; God may anſwer us with the like reaſon, <hi>Is it not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for mee to doe what I will with mine owne prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi> And if any grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe others grow rich, when themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine poore, God may anſwer them, <hi>It is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me to doe what I will with mine owne riches?</hi> And if againe they ſhall grudge, becauſe others are eſteemed and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are neglected, hee may anſwer, <hi>Is it not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me to doe what I will with mine own honours?</hi> And finally, if our preſent ſtate content us not, but that wee grumble for more,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2992:19"/>then God hath thought good to give; he may ſtill reply, (and the anſwer is full of equitie and reaſon) <hi>Freind, I do thee no wrong: may not I doe what I will with mine owne?</hi> And ſure every man would thinke him a proud &amp; preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Begger, that ſhould preſcribe to his Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, what and how much hee ſhould beſtow upon him. And therefore if any ſhould grudge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath no more, God may challenge him as an Incrocker upon his right.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Malecontents ſhould conſider, that the things which they have, how ſmall ſo ever they ſeeme,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2992:19"/>are the <hi>free gifts</hi> of Gods mercy; the leaſt whereof themſelves did no way deſerve, and for everie one of them they owe praiſes and thankeſgiving. For <hi>what haſt thou</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that thou haſt not received?</hi> 1 Cor. 4.7. and <hi>David</hi> when hee and his people had given libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to the building of Gods houſe, <hi>All things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>come of thee, O Lord, and of thine own have we given thee.</hi> 1 Chron. 29.14. And if all the good things, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, bee the gifts of Gods free bountie; then in all reaſon wee ſhould rather give thankes for what we have, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grudge for that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2992:20"/>which wee want. With this conſideration <hi>Moſes</hi> repreſſed the <hi>murmuring</hi> of <hi>Korah</hi> and his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>Seemeth it but a ſmall thing unto you, that the God of Iſrael hath ſeparated you from the Congregation of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, to bring you neare unto himſelfe, to doe the ſervice of the Tabernacle of the Lord, and to ſtand before the Congregation, to miniſter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them? And hee hath brought thee neare unto him, and all thy brethren, the ſons of Levi with thee: and ſeeke yee the Prieſthood alſo?</hi> Numb. 16.9, 10. And ſo if any ſhall murmur for want of greater prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, I may ſay unto them in the phraſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:2992:20"/>God hath done well for you already: he hath put you into a calling among his people, in which yee may live like honeſt men, and by ſeruing God ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in may obtaine eternall life. <hi>Is this but a ſmall thing?</hi> will nothing content you, unleſſe you may be Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, or Barons, or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, or ſome great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders? And if any grudge for want of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wealth, I may ſay, God hath given you compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent meanes, ye want not bread and water to feed you, nor clothes to hide your ſhame. And <hi>thinke yee this but a ſmall thing?</hi> will nothing content you, unleſſe yee may have a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2992:21"/>Gentlemans Lands, or an Aldermans wealth? And againe, if any ſhal repine, for want of more health and ſtrength of body; I may tell them, God hath given you your life, and preſerved you many daies, and continued unto you your ſenſes and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories. And <hi>ſeemeth this but a ſmall thing?</hi> will no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pleaſe you, unleſs ye may haue the ſtrength of a ſouldier? And the like may bee ſaid of all other the like caſes: ſo that if any grudge for want of greater or better gifts, God may challenge him, as a neglecter of greater mercies then hee is any way worthy of.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:2992:21"/>
            <p n="3">3 Such men ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that God beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his bleſſings, as with great difference, ſo with much wiſedome and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And 1. with much wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, becauſe hee ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth them, as that each one ſerveth for the good of another; ſo that it is far better there ſhould bee ſome <hi>Artificers,</hi> and ſome <hi>Labourers,</hi> and ſome <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> then that all ſhould be <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> or Officers of State. And 2. in great mercle, becauſe hee hath not onely given us the uſe of other mens gifts, but alſo becauſe hee doth fit us with thoſe gifts for our ſelves, which are moſt convenient for our condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2992:22"/>Wee reade of the great houſeholder (and this houſeholder is the Lord of heaven:) that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving called for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that he might deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to them his goods to trade with; hee <hi>gave to one five talents, and to another two, and to another one,</hi> and <hi>to every one according to his ſeveral ability,</hi> Mat. 25.15. w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſpeech implyeth thus much, that he that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>one talent,</hi> was not able to imploy two to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters profit; and hee that received <hi>two,</hi> was not able to deale with five: for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one had his meaſure <hi>according to his ability.</hi> And the meaning of this para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is to teach us, that God
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2992:22"/>dealeth ſo with us in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of his gifts. Hee ſtoreth his ſervants with gifts, according as hee ſeeth they are fitted to uſe them. For example, Hee giveth to ſome men, <hi>great wealth</hi> and much riches, as hee did to <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iob;</hi> and to others <hi>much honour</hi> and authoritie, as he did to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el;</hi> and to others <hi>much ſtrength</hi> and valour as hee did to <hi>Sampſon</hi> and <hi>Ieptah;</hi> and this hee did in great wiſdome and mercy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee ſaw theſe men were fit to doe good with theſe gifts;
<note place="margin">Iob. 29.12, 13, 15, 16. &amp; 31.16, 17, 19.20.</note> as namely <hi>Iob</hi> with his wealth, fed the poore, clothed the naked, made the widowes heart
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2992:23"/>to reioyce, &amp;c. And
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gen. 41 56, 57. — 47.25. — 50.20.</note> 
               <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> by his authoritie was a meanes to <hi>ſave much peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple alive.</hi> And
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iudg. 15 18.</note> 
               <hi>Sampſon</hi> by his great ſtrength wrought <hi>great deliverance</hi> for Iſrael. And ſo now a dayes when God giveth wealth, and honours, and ſtrength unto men; wee may well ſuppoſe, that he had made thoſe men able to uſe theſe gifts to good purpoſe, ſaving that men out of their corrupt hearts doe many times pervert the right uſe of Gods gifts. And ſo on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, God giveth to ſome men but little wealth; and hee hath reaſon for it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if they had much they would abuſe it to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2992:23"/>pride or to oppreſſion, or to hinder themſelves in holy duties. To others he giveth a low or a meane place among their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and it is, becauſe if they had a place of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, they would abuſe it, either to ſerve great mens turnes, or to oppreſſe poore men in their cauſes, or to do iniuſtice to their Neighbours. And to others God giueth a weak conſtitution, and a ſickly body; and it is, becauſe if they had greater ſtrength, they might abuſe it to intemperancy, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean luſts; or would take occaſion by it to grow pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous of long life, &amp; careleſſe of heaven and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2992:24"/>ſalvation, or to challenge the field upon everie idle quarrell. Now, if in ſuch caſe God deny us theſe things of the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he meaneth us more good by the want of them, then we could have had by their uſe: then we have great cauſe to bleſſe God, as for giving the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good things which we doe enioy, ſo for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying us theſe ſeeming good things, which we did deſire. Thus <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>It is good for mee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that I have beene afflicted, that I might learne thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</hi> Pſal. 119.71. and ſo ſhould every one of us think and ſay; It is good for mee, that I am a <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:2992:24"/>man, that ſo I may ſerve God and bee free from the tentations of greater places, and it is good for me that I have a <hi>meane eſtate,</hi> that ſo I may ſerve God without the cares and diſtractions that great riches do bring with them. And, It is good for me that I have a <hi>ſickly</hi> body, that ſo I may remember mine end, and prepare for my departing out of the world. And ſo in all other caſes: if wee doe not neglect our owne mercies, that ſtate is beſt for us, which God doth allot unto us: and if our proviſion had been better in the world, our conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might have beene
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2992:25"/>worſe toward God.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the firſt uſe of theſe Doctrines.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond is,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> Wee may learne hence how to price and eſteem the gifts of other men; namely that wee acknowledge their due worth and value, whereſoever, or in whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever wee finde them. For if God doe diſtribute his gifts in ſuch manner, and with ſuch wiſedome as hath been ſhewed; then either to deny them, where they are, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe them below their worth, were no better then to thwart God in an eſpeciall worke of his providence and wiſdome. This, as alſo what our duty
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2992:25"/>is herein, wee may learne by S. <hi>Peter.</hi> He, when the Iewes, out of their zeale to their own Nation, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded</hi> with him for that he had converſed with <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> &amp; his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, ſaying, <hi>Thou wenteſt in to men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed, and didſt eate with them: Peter</hi> made this Apologie for himſelfe, That God by a viſion and a voyce from heaven had taught him, that himſelfe had cleanſed thoſe men, &amp; that <hi>Peter</hi> therfore ſhould not eſteeme them as <hi>pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> and <hi>uncleane;</hi> and that for further proofe hereof he had <hi>powred on them the Holy Ghoſt, as hee had done vpon the Apoſtles in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning:</hi> and then he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2992:26"/>
               <hi>Foraſmuch then, as God gave them the like gift, as he did unto us, who belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt; what was I, that I could withſtand God?</hi> Acts 11.17. In this paſſage wee may note three things. (1) That God had ſhewed extraordinarie mercy to theſe Pagans. They were <hi>aliens from the Common wealth of Iſrael,</hi> and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the Covenant of grace; and yet God had not equalled them to the beſt of his ſervants: hee gave them the <hi>like gift</hi> of the holy Ghoſt, as he had done to his Apoſtles. (2) That S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſeeing this gracious gift of God toward them, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2992:26"/>them for his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, partakers of the ſame grace; though this were a diſparagement to his owne Nation, whoſe glorie it was to bee Gods peculiar people. (3) That if S. <hi>Peter</hi> had done other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if he had ſtill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted them <hi>Aliens,</hi> and forborne their companie, as Infidels, and denied them baptiſme, the ſeale of Gods covenant, in ſo doing hee had <hi>withſtood</hi> God. And the like ſhould be our reſolution alſo. If God have given any gifts or graces to any of our neighbours; whoſoever the men, or whatſoever the gifts bee, though they breede us preiudice in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2992:27"/>our credit, or in our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, or in our prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yet if we ſleight, or debaſe, or denie them, we do what in us lyeth, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe &amp; <hi>withſtand</hi> God in his gratious proceedings. And therefore, as it is ſaid of thoſe Iews, who at firſt contended with <hi>Peter;</hi> that when they had <hi>heard</hi> his defence, <hi>they held their peace, and glorified God</hi> for his mercy to the Gentiles, ſo ſhould wee doe, if it do appeare, that God hath enabled any, though one of our inferiors, with ſome eminent gifts, wee ſhould ceaſe grudging; wee ſhould rather glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God for his mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. A dutie, which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2992:27"/>if it were well learned by us all, it would preſerve our neighbors fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrong, and our ſelves from ſinne. And that wee may both learne and performe it the better, I commend both to you and my ſelfe theſe three rules follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Rule. If God have beſtowed any ſingular bleſſing on any of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, though the height thereof may over-ſhadow us; yet we ſhould readily acknowledge it, to Gods glory who gave it, and to the praiſe of them that do enioy it. Thus the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Iews did in our Saviours time. For when they ſaw Chriſt to heale a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2992:28"/>
               <hi>Palſey</hi> man by his bare word, <hi>they marvelled, and glorified God, who had given ſuch power unto men,</hi> Matt. 9.8. and Matth. 15.31. when <hi>the multitude ſaw the dumbe to ſpeake, the maimed to bee whole, the lame to walke, and the blinde to ſee, they glorified the God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> And in the Chriſtian Church, when the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>heard,</hi> that <hi>Saul</hi> of a <hi>perſecutor</hi> was become a <hi>Preacher, they glorified God in him,</hi> Gal. 1. ult. and Gal. 2.9. <hi>when</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Peter, and Iames and Iohn perceived the grace that was given to Paul</hi> after his converſion, they, though this might obſcure their owne glory, yet <hi>gave him
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2992:28"/>right hand of fellowſhip,</hi> and ioyned with him in the worke of the Miniſterie. And ſo ſhould we doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. If wee know of any man, who out of his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and depth of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is able to unfolde obſcure points in Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; we ſhould acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his gifts, and praiſe God, who hath given ſuch a gift unto men. And if we meete, with another, who though he have no deepe learning, yet hath a readie tongue, and can apply Scriptures to the ſtirring of the conſcience, wee ſhould acknowledge that gift, where we finde it, and give God the praiſe for beſtowing ſuch gifts
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2992:29"/>upon men. And if we hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a third who hath a ready wit to take the preſent occaſion of doing good, or a ſteedie memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that can readily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count what he hath heard or read; wee ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his happineſs that hath it, and praiſe Gods bounty that did give it. And ſo, if wee ſee a Magiſtrate, who hath wiſedome to diſcerne the truth, and conſcience to iudge aright; or if wee meete with an Artificer that is pregnant in his Art, or any profeſſor that hath skil in his profeſſion; wee muſt not denie or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh Gods bleſſings in them, for feare leſt they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2992:29"/>diſparage us; but rather bleſſe God, who hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſuch gifts unto men.</p>
            <p>And this indeed is our dutie, but what is our practiſe? Surely <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> were appointed by God to be Governors to his people; the one for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Church, the other for governing the Commonwealth; &amp; both for the ſafe leading of the people into the promiſed Land: but <hi>Korah</hi> and his Companie grudged them this preheminence. <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, ye take too much upon you, all the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is holy</hi> as well as yee. <hi>Num.</hi> 16.3. And ſo in our daies, ſome will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no Biſhop in the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2992:30"/>Church, nor ſcarſe any King in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; but, as if they were men that had no maſter, they reproach the one, and contemne the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But if wee deſcend lower, <hi>Iacob</hi> obtained a better bleſſing then his brother had, and <hi>Eſau</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him for it. <hi>David</hi> had more honour given him, then <hi>Saul</hi> had, and <hi>Saul</hi> eied him and envied him for it, And <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was more favoured of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then his other bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren were, and they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligned him, and ſtripped off his coate and ſould him into Aegypt. Nay, (which is yet more, and more wicked) <hi>Abel offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2992:30"/>a more excellent ſacrifice then Cain did,</hi> and was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter accepted then he was; and therefore <hi>Cain</hi> hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed downe the head, and was <hi>wroth</hi> with his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in the end mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him? And <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſlew he him?</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Iohn:</hi> and he anſwereth the queſtion with his owne words, <hi>becauſe his owne works were evill, and his brothers righteous</hi> 1 Io. 3.12. And ſo is it among us. The Courtier envieth his fellow, if hee ſtepp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an office ſooner then himſelfe: The Citizen envieth his neighbour if by good huſbandrie hee grow richer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelfe. The Rich man envieth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2992:31"/>thoſe of his owne ranke, if they bee more liberall and free-hearted then himſelfe, yea &amp; the Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioner envieth his or her pew-fellow, if they be taken up to an higher Seate then the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves. And (which exceedeth in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie &amp; ſin) the profane man hateth every man about him, if hee be more charitable in doing good, or more conſcionable in catechizing of his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and more conſtant in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly duties with his familie. And why, but becauſe <hi>his owne workes are evill, and his neighbours good?</hi> And what then may we ſay of ſuch men, but that if God be good in beſtowing his
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2992:31"/>gifts, theſe men are wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that maligne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe them. Our rule is, If any man excell in any gift, in ſharpneſſe of wit, in readineſſe of ſpeech, in uprightneſſe of life  wee ſhould bleſſe God, who hath beſtowed ſuch a gift on one of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, the benefit where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may redound to our ſelves alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A ſecond rule is, If we ſee any, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe much our inferiour, yet that he is gifted in ſome one kinde better then our ſelves; we ſhould acknowledge him therein to be our <hi>ſuperiour,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath pleaſed to make him ſo: and not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2992:32"/>diſdaine to receive helpe from him in that wherein he is above us. Thus <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos</hi> did, of whom S. <hi>Luke</hi> relateth thus; <hi>A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Iew named Apollos, an eloquent man and mighty in the Scriptures, came to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus. This man was inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the way of the Lord, and being fervent in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, hee ſpake and taught di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently the things of the Lord, knowing onely the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of Iohn. And he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſpeake boldly in the Synagogue: whom when A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quila &amp; Priſcilla had heard, they tooke him unto them, and expounded unto him the waie of God more perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Act, 18.24, 25, 26. In this paſſage we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2992:32"/>(1) the facultie or abilitie of this man, Hee was <hi>an eloquent man, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Scriptures, fervent in the Spirit,</hi> and one that taught Chriſt diligently and <hi>boldly:</hi> great bleſſings and principall gifts of God. (2) We may conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this defect, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his great gifts. He <hi>knew onely the Baptiſme of Iohn</hi> .i. he had not been taught, nor did know more of Chriſt, than what <hi>Iohn</hi> B. was woont to teach them that came to his baptiſme: and that was but a little in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that which Chriſt himſelfe did teach while hee was on the Earth, or which the holy Ghoſt had
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2992:33"/>infuſed into the Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, after Chriſts Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion into heaven: ſo that <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> a plaine couple of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, brought up at an han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diecraft; knew more of the grounds of Chriſtianitie, then this learned man did. <hi>Apollos</hi> was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of farre better parts; yet in this point hee came ſhort of an Artificer and his wife. (3) We may note the behaviour of theſe good people in this caſe. <hi>Apollos</hi> ioyned himſelfe to <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> &amp; they <hi>expounded unto him the way of God more perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> Though hee were a learned Divine, yet hee ſcorned not to learne
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2992:33"/>more from them that were much ſhort of his learning. And ſo ſhould wee doe. The deepe Scholar ſhould not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine the plaine Preacher: but rather learne of him, if he can apply a Scripture better then himſelfe. And the popular Preacher that carieth multitudes after him, ſhould not maligne the better learned, but rather learne of him, if he can diſpute more ſolidely then himſelfe. And the rich Citizen and the great Merchant, may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the direction of his poore neighbour, but learne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, if he have more skill in ſome caſes then they, which be his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2992:34"/>have.</p>
            <p>And this is our dutie in this caſe: I would I might ſay that ſo is our practiſe alſo. But <hi>Solomon</hi> telleth us, that when a <hi>City</hi> was <hi>beſieged,</hi> without ſtrength to hold out, <hi>a poore man by his wiſdome deliuered the Citie:</hi> but withall that there was <hi>none that remembred that poore man:</hi> and then hee addeth further, as a daily experiment, that <hi>the poore mans wiſedome is deſpiſed, and his words are not heard.</hi> Eccles. 9.15, 16. implying hereby that the poore mans wiſdome, is not only forgotten, when he hath done good by it; but that it is neglected alſo, when
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2992:34"/>he giveth good counſell for the preſent occaſion. And ſo we finde in the Goſpell, that Chriſts Doctrine was contemned becauſe his parentage was meane, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.22, 24. And iuſt ſo it is now a daies, many a mans good counſell is deſpiſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe himſelfe is of meane place, and deſpicable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. And in this reſpect wee have iuſt cauſe to blame many men: but their pride is intolerable, who thinke they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch their Reverend fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, becauſe God is <hi>no Accepter of perſons;</hi> and yet deſpiſe their brethren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſomewhat younger in yeares, though
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2992:35"/>no whit their inferiour in gifts. Our rule is, that though a man be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe our inferiour, yet if he have ſome one ability in which we come ſhort of him; we ſhould therein acknowledge him to bee our better, and not ſcorne to make uſe of his gifts for our owne good.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A third rule is, If any man bee much our inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our either in calling or in graces; yet we may not deſpiſe his meaneneſſe, becauſe of our greater and better endowments. For if God in wiſedome did ſee it fit, and in mercy hath ſo appointed it for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon good, that one ſhould have both a lower
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2992:35"/>place, and ſome meaner gifts, and another ſhould have both an higher cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and better endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: it will be our wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; I am ſure, it is our dutie, to acknowledge Gods providence and goodneſſe, as well in the meaner, as in the greater and more honorable cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. My meaning is not, that the labourer ſhould be equalled with the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter workema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving man with his Lord or maſter, nor the artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer with the Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor the Commoner with the Alderman. No; God (as I ſaid before) hath made a difference, and ſet a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betweene them:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2992:36"/>and farre be it from mee, to breake downe Gods pale and partition wall. I wiſh that every one may enioy the emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, that God hath beſtowed upon him: but I ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that the pooreſt hath his ſtation and his place among his neighbors, which becauſe God hath inveſted him into, men may not without ſinne thruſt him out of it. For example, the pooreſt man that is, hath three prerogatives given him from God. 1 God hath made him a man, endued with a reaſonable ſoule, and portraied out after Gods owne Image; and wee may not denie him
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2992:36"/>a right in thoſe things, which belong to life and livelihood, and are due to the nature of mankinde. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, God hath made him a Chriſtian, and hath imparted unto him the merits and the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ieſus Chriſt: and wee may not denie unto him a right to the word and to the Sacraments &amp; ſalvation. Thirdly, God hath made him a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him a Calling, in which he may doe ſervice for the common good; &amp; wee may not denie him the protection of laws, &amp; the right of a ſubiect. And
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2992:37"/>therefore if wee deſpiſe any ſuch man, as if he were no-body, and ſtood only for a Cypher in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; we ſhall thereby diſhonor God, who with much wiſedome, and in great mercy, hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to be what hee is. To this purpoſe <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that mocketh the poore, reproacheth him that made him.</hi> Prov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, that if any man contemne the poore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is poore, or of low degree, the reproach caſt againſt the creature, lighteth upon the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who hath made him to be ſuch. And ſo, and by the ſame reaſon I may ſay, If any man contemne a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2992:37"/>plaine Chriſtian, becauſe he is not quick-witted; or an honeſt meaning man, becauſe he is not hot-ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited; or a countrey bred man, becauſe he is not ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilized; or a Citizen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle race; or an Artificer, becauſe hee is not in place of command; or a Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labourer, becauſe he is not free of the Citie, &amp;c. eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch ſcorner of his poore neighbour, reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth God himſelf, whoſe good pleaſure it is, as wel that ſome ſhould bee in meane places, as that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould have higher; and all for the good of the Church, and the honour of the Almighty. And
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2992:38"/>from hence it is, that <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, that hee <hi>deſpiſed not the cauſe of his man-ſervant, nor of his maid-ſervant, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they contended with him.</hi> Iob 31.13. And ver. 15. he giveth a reaſon for it. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>did not hee that made me in the wombe, make him? and did not one faſhion us in the wombe?</hi> And in like ſort ſhould wee ſay and doe. We may deſpiſe no mans place or calling, as long as it is of Gods making. But if wee have to deale with a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, or the pooreſt boy about the ſtreets; we muſt acknowledge him not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a creature, whom God hath endued with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortallſoule; nor onely
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2992:38"/>reſpect him as a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath appointed to be heire of eternal life; but alſo as a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth or church, who in his place may doe ſervice for the common good. And conſequently we may deny no man the right, that belongeth to ſuch a place and calling.</p>
            <p>And this againe is our dutie; but where is our practiſe anſwerable ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Surely <hi>Ahab</hi> thought <hi>Naboth</hi> unworthy of ſo good a vine-yard, as might bee fit to make a <hi>Kings gardon.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee and his Queene turned <hi>Naboth</hi> out of his inheritance, nay took him away out of the world,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2992:39"/>that they might enioy his poſſeſſions. And ſo now a daies, there be men, that thinke lands and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances to be <hi>too good</hi> for an Hoſpitall; and Lordſhips and Honors not to be ſit for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of Students: &amp; what (ſay they) ſhould <hi>Almeſmen doe with ſuch dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities as may better beſeeme a Lord or a Gentleman?</hi> And ſo they do, at leaſt they would turne them out of their inheritances to feed upon the bare Common. Againe, the Prophets co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of the Iudges of their time, that they did <hi>not judge, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not the cauſe of the fatherleſſe and the widow.</hi> And ſo among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, if a poore neighbour
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2992:39"/>ſhould have a controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with a rich merchant, or a ſhop-keeper with an Alderman, or a common ſubject with a Lord or a Privie Counſellor, yee would eaſily gheſſe which way the balla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce would be ſwayed. It is ſeldome ſeen, but that the greatnes of the perſon weigheth down the goodnes of the cauſe; and the poore man is not permitted to enjoy the benefit of the Law, &amp; the libertie of the Land, where he liveth. Againe, <hi>Nathan</hi> telleth <hi>David</hi> in a parabolicall reſemblance, that a <hi>Rich man</hi> tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the only <hi>lambe</hi> which a <hi>poore man</hi> had; that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he might give enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2992:40"/>to his friend. But in our daies wee finde it in reall performance, that Great men doe not ſeldome take away the poore mans right, to defraie their owne char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Nay, our age pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth yet further in this impietie. It may be ſeene in moe Pariſhes then one, that Great men thinke their poore neighbours unworthy of any ſeate in the Church; and thruſt them out of their fathers houſe, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves may bee placed alone in the chiefeſt roomes: a paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell example whereto I have not yet found either in Scriptures, or in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſtories; and I pray
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2992:40"/>God, it may ſpread no further, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered people of this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt age. But howſoever, our rule is; If God have given us ſuperioritie or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie above others; we may enioy it, with Gods good will and liking: but ſo as that wee forget not, that our pooreſt neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are men, are Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of the civil Body: and therefore wee cannot without wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of men, and diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of God, denie them thoſe priviledges, which belong to ſuch places. And thus much for the firſt Note, and the two points of doctrine ariſing from it.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:2992:41"/>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>2</label> I note, that though <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> had their ſeverall gifts, and each not a little differing from other; yet they quarrelled not one the other, nor did one ſeeke to out-vie and obſcure his fellow; but like friends, with one heart and minde, they went out together, they ranne both together, and both of them came to the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, and looked in, and beheld what had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened; and having done what they came for, they departed, like loving frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to their own home. By all which it appeareth, that though they had <hi>differing</hi> gifts, yet they
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2992:41"/>had <hi>agreeing</hi> mindes; and did ioyne together in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after Chriſt. And hence the Obſervation is, that</p>
            <p>Good Chriſtians and true diſciples of Chriſt muſt not breake the unity of the Spirit,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>3</label> for any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of gifts. Or more briefely thus; Differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of gifts ſhould not breed in us diſtraction of minds.</p>
            <p>The proofes that I will bring for further confirmation of this point, are of two ſorts: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as conclude the point in the generall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent: and 2 ſuch as prove it by ſeverall and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar inſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">I.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>1</label> And firſt for gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2992:42"/>proofes, wee have a plaine place in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.24, 25. The words are, <hi>God hath tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered the body together, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given more abundant honour to that part, which lacked, that there ſhould be us ſchiſme in the body, But that the members ſhould have the ſame care one for another.</hi> In theſe words we may note three things for our purpoſe. (1) Gods workmanſhip in framing the naturall body, he hath tempered it together, ſaith the Apoſtle: hee meaneth that as God hath made ſeverall parts, each of which hath its different office, ſo hee hath fitted and (if I may
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2992:42"/>ſo ſpeake) hath ſodered the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together in ſuch ſort, as every one doth ſerve for the uſe and benefit of another. (2) Gods wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in framing this temper; &amp; that is, he hath ſo tempered it, that hee hath <hi>given the more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant honour to that part which lacked</hi> .i. whereas ſome parts were of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner uſe, or leſſe comely feature, hee hath withall graced them with ſome other priviledge, that may procure them as much honour. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, If any part be noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and unſeemely to looke on, he hath ſet that in ſuch a corner, as where it may bee hid and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2992:43"/>from the ſenſes. And if any part bee made to ſerve for a baſe or meane office, he hath made it to bee of ſo much the more neceſſary uſe: ſo that a man may better ſpare an eye, or an hand or an eare, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſmalleſt <hi>ſinke-hole,</hi> by which the filth of the body is purged. Thus God ſhewed great wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in tempering the whole body with ſome proportionable reſpects, that might commend it. Thirdly, we may note the end of this temperature: and that, as it is ſet downe in the Text, is twofold. 1 Negatiue, that there ſhoud bee <hi>no ſchiſme</hi> or no diſagreement among the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2992:43"/>members. And 2 affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that the <hi>members ſhold have the ſame care one for another.</hi> Now (to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this) long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to our purpoſe) we muſt not think, that when the Apoſtle doth thus par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ſet down the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of mans body, with the ſeverall offices &amp; uſes belonging unto it, that hee meant to read us an <hi>Anatomie</hi> lecture, or to teach us principles of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie; as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> when he wrote <hi>de partibus anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium:</hi> but that by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon from the naturall body of man, he meant to teach Divinitie leſſons concerning the Myſticall body of Chriſt; as may
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2992:44"/>and doth appeare by the direct ſcope and intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Chapter. And if thus we underſtand the text (and ſo in all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wee muſt;) then wee have this Doctrine from it, that in the myſtical bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which is the Church, ſeverall men have their ſeverall gifts and their diſtinct functions, yet ſo tempered and fitted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; as that there neede not, nor there ought not to bee any ſchiſme or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord among men, becauſe of their divers and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing gifts: Nay rather the difference of gifts is a good reaſon to ſtabliſh the agreement of their mindes: becauſe every one
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2992:44"/>having uſe of another, and benefit from the gifts of another, all ſhould have a ioynt care to uphold and preſerve each other. And ſo in concluſion, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie of gifts is ſo farre from cauſing of diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that it ought in all reaſon, to breed unitie of affections. And this for the firſt kinde of proofes.</p>
            <p n="2">II.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>2</label> My ſecond is from inſtances of ſuch differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in mens gifts, as many times doe, but never ſhould, cauſe any diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of minde. And theſe differences, (ſo farre, as I can obſerve them) are eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially three. 1 diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of knowledge, and (which followeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon)
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2992:45"/>difference of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 2 differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an vertues: and 3 diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in growth and in degrees of grace.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The firſt is <hi>Difference in knowledge</hi> and in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for God doth not give a like meaſure of knowledge unto all men. Some are <hi>Babes,</hi> and <hi>haue need</hi> to bee fed with <hi>milke;</hi> and others are growne men, and can digeſt ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger meate: as the Apoſtle diſtinguiſheth <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.12, 13, 14. And his meaning is, that ſome Chriſtians were ſo unskilfull in the Chriſtian faith, that they had neede to be taught their firſt principles; and others were ſo well
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2992:45"/>grounded, that they could underſtand deepe and darke Myſteries. Beſides, among men, who are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall in habituall skill, yet God ſometime revealeth a truth to one, which hee imparteth not unto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and hence it happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that though mens ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall knowledge may bee alike, yet they are not equall in the actuall apprehenſion of ſome truthes. And by reaſon of this difference in mens knowledge, there grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a difference in their opinions alſo: as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle obſerved it in his owne time, that thoſe who were <hi>ſtrong</hi> in the faith, .i. who knew their
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2992:46"/>Chriſtian libertie, and what it imported; theſe <hi>beleeved that they might lawfully eate</hi> of ſuch meates as <hi>Moſes</hi> had forbidden, but they who were <hi>weake</hi> in the faith, and did not fully underſtand the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that Chriſt had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for us; theſe did content themſelves <hi>to eate herbes,</hi> rather then to touch any thing, which the Law did not allow, as appeareth in the Apoſtles Text <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.2 &amp;c. Theſe and ſuch differences in opinion, as theſe be, there are many times found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the beſt and beſt learned of Gods ſervants. And theſe differences in opinion, doe many times
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2992:46"/>breede diſcord in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; &amp; cauſe endleſſe ſtrife among men of the ſame Church; each ſide ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more for victorie then for truth: and ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide enduring his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, who croſſeth them in the leaſt fancy. But the Apoſtles rule is to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; <hi>Let not him that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth deſpiſe him that eateth not; and let not him that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not, judge him that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,</hi> Rom. 14.3. In which words it is worth our noting, to ſee, how the Apoſtle doth fit his leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or rules to the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the differing and diſſenting parties. For he that eateth in the Apoſtles phraſe, is ſuch a one, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:2992:47"/>well inſtructed in the uſe of his Chriſtian liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, was well aſſured that he might lawfully eate of things forbidden by the Law, becauſe Chriſt had freed him from that legall bondage. Now ſuch a man, ſo well grounded in the rules of faith, would be apt to deſpiſe others, who knew not ſo much, and to eſteeme them as ſhallow and ſoft-witted men. And therefore the Apoſtle fitteth him with this leſſon, <hi>Let not him that eateth, deſpiſe him that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not.</hi> Contrariwiſe, he that did thinke himſelfe tyed to obſerve <hi>Moſes</hi> his Law, and therefore out of tenderneſſe of conſcience;
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2992:47"/>and for feare of offending God, did abſtaine from the prohibited meates: this man would be apt to cenſure others, who did eate of thoſe meates, as Libertines and looſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and men of large co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. And therfore the Apoſtle fitteth him with an anſwerable leſſon, <hi>Let not him that eateth not, judge him that eateth.</hi> So in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion, though the one ſide had the truth, yet the Apoſtle will permit ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide to quarrell or cenſure the other for dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in opinion. And the like rule the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle giveth us, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Let as many, as be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, be thus minded: and if
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2992:48"/>in any thing yee be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveile it unto you. Nevertheleſſe, whereto wee have attained, let us walke by the ſame rule, let us minde the ſame thing.</hi> In which words I note two things: (1) That the Apoſtle voucheth the truth of his doctrine to be ſuch, as that no well grounded Chriſtian can denie it to be true; <hi>Let as many, as be perfect, be thus minded.</hi> (2) Hee directeth us what to do, in caſe any man do diſſent from us in this truth: and that is firſt to expect till God do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten him &amp; ſhew him his errour: and ſecondly, to keepe friendſhip and communion with him, &amp;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2992:48"/>to joyne with him in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God according to thoſe common truths, wherein both ſides agree. This is the Apoſtles cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable and peaceable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, in caſe that men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with us in the maine grounds of faith, do diſſent from us in ſome other opinions. Which rule of charitie, if it were followed in theſe quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling dayes, the peace of the Church would not be ſo rent in pieces, as each day it is by factious and cenſorious ſpirits. But yee my Brethren, that ye may love peace the better, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, I pray you, that the Apoſtle permitteth not them, who have the truth
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2992:49"/>on their ſide, to breake the <hi>bond of peace,</hi> no, not with them, whom they know to be in an errour. And how much more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable then is it, if they who are erroneous in their opinions, and idle in their proofes; be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all both obſtinate and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious? And yet uſually ſo it is. For we finde, that the Egyptians were ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous of <hi>eating with the Hebrews,</hi> when the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, for ought wee reade, were not afraid of eating with them, Gen. 43.32. And
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iohn. 9.22, 23. and 12.42. and 16.2.</note> the Scribes and Phariſes excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated Chriſt, &amp; all that acknowledged him to be the Meſſias. But
<note n="b" place="margin">Matt. 23.2, 3.</note> our
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2992:49"/>Lord acknowledged the Scribes and Phariſes, though corrupt. Teachers, yet <hi>to ſit in Moſes his chaire,</hi> and to bee lawfull paſtors of the Church, whom men were bound to obey. And in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, the Donatiſts were ſo fierce and violent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholiks, that
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>In bareſin ſchiſma ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terunt, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia Chriſti. de loto terraru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> orbe perie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ubi fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa eſt: at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que in Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca &amp; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati parte re manſerit. — Audent rebaptizare Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li os, ubi ſe ampliùs baereticos eſſe firmarunt: quum Eccleſiae Catholicae univerſae placuerit, nec in ipſis bae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticis baptiſma communc reſcendere,</hi> Aug. de haereſ. cap. 69.</note> they would not allow them to <hi>be a Church,</hi> or to have any true <hi>baptiſme:</hi> &amp; therefore, if any one fell from the Catholikes to the Donatiſts ſide, they <hi>baptized him over againe,</hi> as if his former baptiſme
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2992:50"/>were nothing worth. But the Catholikes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Donatiſts, though heretikes, yet to have a Church in which true <hi>baptiſme</hi> was admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred. And
<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quid vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis vultis ſaciamus, qui quando vobis dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ut cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam noſtram &amp; veſtram patienter audiatis, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtis niſi ſuperbire &amp; inſanire?</hi> Aug. epiſt. 166. ad Donatiſtas pag. 257. C &amp; ibid. pag 258. G. <hi>Veſtri Epiſcopi conventi à nobis, nunquam nobiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um pacificè conferre vol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erunt, quaſi fugientes cum pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus loqui.</hi>
               </note> when the Catholikes offered them a <hi>quiet</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,</hi> they inſolently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected them, as unworthy to be talked with. Yea &amp; when the
<note n="e" place="margin">V. Opratum adv. Parmen. lib. 1 in principio: &amp; Auguſt, in Pſal 32. Conc. 2. Pag 81. &amp; cont. Gaudent. l 2. c. 11 p. 243. C.</note> Catholikes called them <hi>Brethren,</hi> they ſcornfully refuſed the name of brotherhood at their hands. In all which who doth not ſee, that pride and errour did ſtill
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2992:50"/>goe together; and that the true beleevers ſhewed charitie toward their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, when the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Gods truth were implicable and peeviſh, and would accept no termes of pacification and concord? And iuſt ſo is the caſe now a daies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene us and our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries in religion.</p>
            <p>For firſt, they of the Roman Church doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne us for miſcreants and Caſtawaies; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us no place neither in heaven nor in the church: but we, as the true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes were woont to doe, grant the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be a Church, though it be a <hi>bad</hi> one; and confeſſe that in that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2992:51"/>Church there is
<note n="*" place="margin">See the learned an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of <hi>R. B.</hi> to Fiſhers Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his third Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference <hi>pag.</hi> 67, 68, 69.</note> a <hi>poſsibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> to be ſaved, though it be with <hi>difficulty</hi> &amp; much danger. They againe caſt out our name as abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and unworthie their naming: but wee ſay of them as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did of the Donatiſts, We will
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tune eſſe deſine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres noſtri, ſi deſierint di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, Pater noſter,</hi> Aug. in Pſal. 32. <hi>concio.</hi> 2. pag. 81. A.</note> 
               <hi>not ceaſe to call them brethren;</hi> as long as <hi>they do not ceaſe to ſay, Our father.</hi> And as <hi>Optatus</hi> ſaid of thoſe heretikes, ſo we ſay of theſe,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sunt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue dubio fratres, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vis non boni</hi> Optat adu: Parmé. l. 1 in prine. fol. 2.</note> 
               <hi>They be our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, though they bee but bad ones.</hi> But what? And doe we hereby give any ſuch advantage to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, as that either our brethren at home ſhould blame us for our lenitie, or our enemies
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2992:51"/>abroad ſhould glorie in our teſtimonie? Surely, all the advantage, that the Romaniſt gaine by this, is the ſame, that the Aeygptians had againſt the Hebrewes, and the Iewes againſt Chriſt, &amp; the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts againſt the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Church. And if they will glory herein, they ſhall glorie in their pride, which wiſe men will ſay, is all one as to
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ioh. 13.35.</note> 
               <hi>glorie in their ſhame.</hi> As for us, we hold it more honor, to glorie in our Maſters live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is to ſhew cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie towards all that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe his name. But yet ſomewhat to mitigate their pride, we tell them further that if any of them
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:2992:52"/>be ſaved, it is by vertue of that common truth wherein they agree with us; it is not by that pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar faith, which they hold of their owne. And if they will renounce thoſe errors, which they have mingled with this truth, their faith will bee the more pure, &amp; their ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſo doubtfull. Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we are ſtill reſolved to keep the Apoſtles rule, which is,
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Ephe. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>to follow the truth in love:</hi> that is, ſo to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the truth as that we do not breake the bond of peace, where wee have any meanes to keepe it.</p>
            <p>Secondly our unkinde brethren of the <hi>German</hi> Churches, though they
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2992:52"/>agree with us in the maine points of faith, yet doe ſcornefully reject our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of their friendſhip and brother-hood.
<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Audio Lutherum cum at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oci invectiva. no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vos, quam in nos omnes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupiſſe. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin ad Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 57.</note> 
               <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> began with <hi>bitter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives</hi> againſt <hi>Calvin</hi> &amp; his fellowes; but
<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Saepe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſolitus ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Etiâſi me Diabolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caret, me ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men hoc iſti honoris ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biturum, ut inſigne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Det, ſervum ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcam.</hi> Calvin. ibi.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> did give ſo in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſpect to <hi>Luther,</hi> as that beſide the eſteeme of his gifts, <hi>he was wont to ſay of him; Although</hi> Luther <hi>ſhould call me Devill, yet will I do him the honour to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him for an excellent ſervant of God.</hi> Thus theſe two Chiefetaines began; and their followers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to treade in their Leaders ſteps. In the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference at Mompelgart (where <hi>Beza, Muſculus,</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:2992:53"/>and others did appeare for the French Church, and <hi>Iacobus Andreae</hi> and <hi>Lucas Oſiander</hi> with their Aſſociats for the other ſide) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after ſome time ſpent in diſputation, the differences betweene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could not bee accorded; Beza
<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rogat ut Bezam cum ſuu Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis profra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcant, &amp; dextra sfra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitat is if<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis porrigere velint.</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loq. Mom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelg. in fine pag. 566.</note> 
               <hi>deſired</hi> of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of Wittenberg, <hi>that they would acknowledge him and his fellow Miniſters for their Brethren, and would</hi> give them the <hi>right hands of brotherhood;</hi> the other Divines made them a churliſh and uncharitable anſwere,
<note n="(h)" place="margin">— <hi>eos profratri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere non poſſint.</hi> ibid. pag. 667.</note> 
               <hi>that they could not acknowledge them for their brethren.</hi> And in after times, others of each ſide, have ſhewed the like tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2992:53"/>as whoſoever ſhall deſire to ſee, needes no more but to reade the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter writings of
<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Meiſner. Philoſ p. Sobrit par.</hi> 1. Sect. 2. cap. 3. pa. 547.</note> 
               <hi>Meiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerus,</hi> and the temperate and charitable judgement of
<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vedel. Kational. Theolog.</hi> l. 1 c. 7. pa. 67, 68. &amp; ca. 9 pag. 84.</note> 
               <hi>Vedelius;</hi> the one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor in Wittenberg, and the other in Geneva. I ſay no more, but onely wiſh that they who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the faith, that is taught in the French Church, wold imitate the moderation and ſobrietie of the learned Doctors who have taught and maintained it. And ſo I leave this firſt difference, which is in Opinions and judgement.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The next is, a <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Chriſtian ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</hi>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:2992:54"/>For though all true Chriſtians be ſanctified in everie part, and have a portion of all neceſſarie graces yet God diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth theſe graces in ſuch a different manner and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that in ſeverall men ſome are eminent and glorious, and other are ſcarſe conſpicuous or to be ſeene. For example, to one man God giveth a good meaſure of patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but not ſo much courage; to another he giveth cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage for the truth, but not ſo much moderation or judgement; &amp; to another he giveth mildnes of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but not ſo much zeale in Gods ſervice: ſo that we may ſay of one, that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2992:54"/>he is patient, or moderate, or of a meeke minde; but not ſo fitly, that he is zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, or couragious, or conſtant in his purpoſe. And in this caſe I ſay, that <hi>difference of ſuch vertues</hi> ſhould not cauſe diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of minde; but in this diverſitie of graces wee ſhould ſerve God with unitie of minde. To this purpoſe S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath a good note upon the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Zaccheus</hi> and the Centurion, both of them mentioned in the Goſpell. Of the Centurion wee reade; that when Ieſus was coming to his houſe, he <hi>ſent friends</hi> to ſtop him by the way: for (ſaith he) <hi>Lord I am not worthie, that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2992:55"/>thou ſhouldeſt enter under my roofe.</hi> Luke. 7.6. But for <hi>Zaccheus,</hi> Chriſt had no ſooner called to him, <hi>Zac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus make haſte, and come downe; for to day I muſt abide at thy houſe:</hi> but hee <hi>made haſt, &amp; came down, &amp; received him with joy.</hi> Luke. 19.5, 6. In which ſtories we may note, that theſe two, both of them good men, did ſhew two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, &amp; in ſome ſort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie vertues: The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion hindered Chriſt from coming to his houſe, becauſe he thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>unworthie</hi> of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: &amp; herein he ſhewed much humilitie and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his Saviour. But <hi>Zaccheus</hi> at the firſt word
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2992:55"/>received Chriſt into his houſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neque liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt interſe ant quiſquam corum ſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri prapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, Zac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeus et ille Centurio, quum alter corum gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ſuam ſuſceperit Dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dixerit Nöſum dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, ut intres ſubiectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Amho Salvatoſe bonorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes diverſe &amp; quaſt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mbopec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tis miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, ambo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordiam coaſeqanti.</hi> Aug epiſt 118. <hi>ad Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuar.</hi> ca. 3. pag, 190</note> and entertained him with all readines and by this he ſhewed great affection and love to his Lord. Now concerning the difference in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation is this; [<hi>Neque litigaverunt inter ſe, &amp;c.</hi>] Theſe two good men, for all their difference in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noring Chriſt <hi>did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the one againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor did either of them prefer himſelfe before his fellow.</hi> Had they been like ſome hot ſpirits in our daies, <hi>Zaceheus</hi> might have blamed the Centurion either for incivilitie, or for lacke of faith, that he would forbid Chriſt to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:2992:56"/>come into his houſe: and the Centurion might have condemned him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for his boldneſſe or want of due reverence that he durſt receive the Lord of glorie into a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cotage. But <hi>non litiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt,</hi> they ſtrove both of them how they might beſt honour their Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; they did not one ſtrive againſt another for honouring him in a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent maner. No, ſaith this good father, <hi>both of them did honour Chriſt in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, and in ſome ſort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie manner;</hi> and <hi>both of them being miſerable by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their ſinnes, did both of them obtaine mercy</hi> to free the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from their ſinnes.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2992:56"/>This is the note of S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> upon the different qualities of theſe holy men. A like, but more direct note may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the different and contrarie behaviour of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, and <hi>Ieſus</hi> our <hi>Saviour.</hi> Of them both wee thus reade in one place; <hi>Iohn came ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cating nor drinking; and they ſay, Hee hath a devill. The Sonne of man came eating and drinking; and they ſay, Behold, a man gluttonous &amp; a wine-bibber, a friend of Publicanes and ſinners.</hi> Matt. 11.18, 19. But what ſaid they two, that lived in this ſo diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent a manner? What ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the one of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2992:57"/>the other? Why, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid of <hi>Chriſt; Behold the Lamb of God, which taketh away the ſinnes of the world.</hi> And <hi>This is he, of whom I ſaid, There commeth a man after mee, who is preferred before mee,</hi> &amp;c. Iohn 1.27, 29. <hi>the latchet of whoſe ſhooes I am not worthy to ſtoope downe and unlooſe.</hi> Mar. 1.7. And <hi>Ieſus</hi> contrarily, he ſaid of <hi>Iohn; Hee is a Prophet, and more then a Prophet.</hi> —and, <hi>among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that are borne of women, there hath not riſen a greater, then Iohn the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt.</hi> Matt. 11.9, 11. In which paſſages, wee may for our learning conſider three things: (1) The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent practiſe of <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and their contrary
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2992:57"/>courſe of life; <hi>Iohn came neyther eating nor drinking,</hi> and <hi>the Sonne of man came eating and drinking.</hi> The meaning is, that <hi>Iohn</hi> lived an auſtere life, and kept a kinde of continuall faſt, as became him who was the Preacher of Repentance: but Ieſus lived a ſociable life, and kept company with men in a friendly manner, as was fit for him who brought the glad ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Goſpell. Such was their different and contrary courſe of life. (2) Note, the Cenſure which the Iews gave of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both. They were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with neyther of them: <hi>Iohn</hi> for his auſterity lived not like a man; he doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:2992:58"/>had a devill: and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus for his familiaritie, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not like a ſober man, he was a glutton and a wine-bibber. This was their Cenſure. (3) Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the mutuall teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, that <hi>Ieſus</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> did giue, the one of the other: <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Iohn, Hee is more then a Prophet,</hi> &amp; the chiefe among the ſonnes of women: and <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> that hee was more then a man, and ſo farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove himſelfe, that he was not worthie to untie his ſhooes. [<hi>Non litigaverunt inter ſe</hi>] Theſe two rare men of verie differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions, yet did not ſtrive one againſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; they ſtrove how
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:2992:58"/>each might moſt honour the other. And this may teach us, what we ſhould doe. If we cavill at other mens vertues, and deprave their doings, when they agree not to our fanſie, we are not like either <hi>Ieſus</hi> or <hi>Iohn:</hi> wee reſemble rather the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes</hi> who were pleaſed nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>fulnes</hi> nor <hi>faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> But if we will imitate <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Ieſus,</hi> then if wee ſee in divers men diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent vertues, we muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God in them all. And if one man bee ſociable like Chriſt, when we are ſevere like <hi>Iohn;</hi> and if another be humble like the Centurion, when wee are hearty like <hi>Zac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus;</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:2992:59"/>and if a third bee meeke like <hi>Moſes,</hi> while wee are zealous like <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas:</hi> wee may not judge them, becauſe they agree not with us; but rather wee ſhould praiſe God, who by ſuch different te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, hath found the moe wayes to ſet forth his owne glory.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the ſecond Difference.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The third is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in perfection or growth in grace. For a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſts Scholars, ſome are <hi>children in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> and others are of ripe age; and, ſome are <hi>babes in Chriſt,</hi> &amp; in great part but <hi>carnall</hi> ſtill, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> &amp; well
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2992:59"/>growne Chriſtians: as the Apoſtle alſo hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved 1 Cor. 3.1, 2. Heb. 5.13.14. And this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence though it make a plaine diſtinction in the graces of God, yet it ſhould make no diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the mindes of men, For ſo the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Him that is weake in the faith, receive, but not to doubtfull diſputations.</hi> Rom. 14.1. and, <hi>Brethren,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>if a man bee over-taken in a fault, ye which are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, reſtore ſuch a man in the ſpirit of meekneſſe.</hi> Gal. 6.1. And of our Saviour it is ſaid, <hi>A bruiſed reede ſhall hee not breake, and ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king flax ſhall he not quench.</hi> Mat. 12.20. The meaning
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2992:60"/>is, that our Lord doth not contemne the ſmalleſt ſparkes of grace, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the leaſt degree of goodnes, whereſoever he findeth it. And agreeably hereunto <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth his counſell. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing requeſted by a godly Matrone to give her ſome <hi>rules of prayer,</hi> for her ſelfe and her family; in which there were divers others of the ſame ſex: among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things he telleth her,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug epiſt</hi> 121.<hi>ad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum. cap ult pag.</hi> 214.</note> that <hi>fervencie in prayer is much helped by faſting</hi> and chaſtening of the body; for the right uſe whereof hee giveth her this caveat, [<hi>Faciat quaeque veſtrûm, quod poterit,</hi>] <hi>Let everyone of you do, what ſhe ſhall be able.</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:2992:60"/>Some can faſt more, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who are of a weaker conſtitution, cannot doe ſo much: let every one doe as ſhe may, without harm to her health, which God deſireth not. Hee addeth further, (which is moſt proper to this purpoſe) [<hi>Quaeminùs valet, non im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediat plùs valentem; &amp; quae plùs valet, non urgeat minùs valentem.] Let not her, that is leſſe able, pull her backe that can doe more; and let not her, that is more able, preſſe her forward, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe ſo much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the wiſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of that learned Father: which if wee would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace &amp; follow, it would increaſe our piety toward
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:2992:61"/>God, our charitie toward men, and our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation and peace. For ſo wee ſhould ſerve God with united hearts, bleſſe God for his mercies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our brethren, and poſſeſſe that peace in our owne ſoules, which would not onely make us content with our owne gifts, but would teach us to make uſe of other mens alſo. And ſo the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Gods bleſſings, diſtributed among his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, would be as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſtinct voyces, which make the better melody, and the ſweeter muſicke.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you then, let no diverſitie of Gods gifts cauſe any diſtraction in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2992:61"/>your mindes: but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, let not frivolous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of greatnes, or idle conceits of your owne worth, or ſelfe-liking co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons about trifles, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your mutuall accord in Gods ſervice. A thing which I do the rather ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh you of: becauſe I heare, that abroad among our neighbours, and I ſee that at home among our ſelves, there is ſprung up a profane kinde of pride, which like that of the Phariſes, maketh ſome brethren, but moe ſiſters to ſtrive for the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt roomes in our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. One thinketh her ſelfe good enough to ſit with her betters; and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:2992:62"/>thinketh her ſelfe too good to ſit with her fellowes; and a third is not content to ſit aloft, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſhe may ſit alone; as if ſhee were ſorie to have any body to accompany her towards heaven. Yea and many of inferiour ſort profeſſe their diſcontent, becauſe they are not pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced according to their worth; as if they meant to tell the world, that they think better of themſelves then all their neighbours doe beſides. But I beſeech you, lay aſide theſe great thoughts, at leaſt when ye come into Gods houſe; and conſider a little what <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> did. They had their different gifts,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:2992:62"/>both of minde and of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and of place; and yet they ranne together to ſeeke Chriſt, do ye thinke that there is ſo much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betweene you and your next neighbors, that yee will not ſit together to heare Chriſt while he is teaching you the way of ſalvation? Againe, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwhat <hi>David</hi> ſaid; <hi>I was glad</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>when they ſaid unto mee, Let us goe into the houſe of the Lord.</hi> Pſal. 122.1. Good man! hee rejoyced to have the company of his neighbours in ſerving of God: and if wee had his ſpirit, wee would bee of his minde. Wee would be glad if wee might have
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:2992:63"/>our neighbours to beare us co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie in Gods houſe, and glad if wee had any ſpare roome in our ſeates to entertaine them in: that ſo wee might ſit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and heare toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and pray together, and goe chearfully toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther towards heaven and eternall happineſſe. For ſurely, none ſhall ever enter into heaven, but they which have ſo much humilitie, as to thinke that their neighbours may bee their fellowes in this iourney, and ſo much charitie, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire their company to goe with them thither. And ſo I have done with theſe Meditations: I only now
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2992:63"/>pray, The God of peace grant us to bee like-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 48. <hi>Line.</hi> 16. <hi>for</hi> not equalled <hi>r.</hi> now equalled 58.16. and more <hi>r.</hi> or more 61.10. this defect <hi>r.</hi> his defect 97.6. implicable <hi>r.</hi> implacable 98. <hi>in the margin fine</hi> r. <hi>ſine</hi> 99.4. Romaniſt <hi>r.</hi> Romaniſts 107.7. the difference <hi>r.</hi> this difference.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
